Register of the Nikolai Valentinov Papers, 1912-1964
Hoover Institution Archives
Nikolai Valentinov Papers,
1912-1964
65003
Valentinov, N. (Nikolai), 1879-1964
9 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope 3.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, clippings, reports, and photographs, relating to Russian revolutionary movements and emigre life, Imperial Russian and Soviet agricultural and economic policies, labor movements, Menshevism, and political events in Russia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1965.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924.; Rossiiskaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia rabochaia partiia.; Mensheviks.; Agriculture--Soviet Union.; Communism.; Labor movement--Russia.; Land tenure--Russia.; Peasantry--Russia.; Revolutionaries--Russia.; Russians in foreign countries.; Socialism--Russia.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Economic policy.; Russia--History.; Soviet Union--Industries.
Biographical Note
1879 Born, Morshansk, Tambov Province, Russia
1897 Enters Petersburg Institute of Technology, joins revolutionary movement and is exiled to Ufa
1900 Returns from exile, studies at Kiev Polytechnic Institute, is arrested for revolutionary activities, escapes to Europe
1903-1904 Meets Lenin in Geneva, joins Social Democratic Party (Bolsheviks)
1905 Returns to Russia, breaks with Lenin and the Bolshevik Party. Joins the Mensheviks
1905-1917 Begins lifelong engagement in journalism. Contributes to Russkoe Slovo and Kievskaia Mysl'. Resigns from Menshevik Party
1917-1927 Edits Torgovo-Promyshlennaia Gazeta, organ of the Supreme Council of National Economy of the U.S.S.R.
1928 Emigrates to Paris, France. Publishes in emigré and French press
1953 Author, Vstrechi s Leninym. English translation published in 1968 as Encounters with Lenin
1954 Author, Dva Goda s Simvolistami. English translation published in 1969 as Two Years With the Symbolists
1964 Dies, Paris, France
1969 Author (posthumously), The Early Years of Lenin
Scope and Content
This collection consists mostly of the correspondence and writings of Nikolai Vol'skii, also known under the pseudonyms Nikolai Valentinov and E. Iur'evskii. The collection covers the period of his emigration in Paris between 1932-1962. Of special interest is the first part of the collection, which includes his correspondence with fellow socialists in the emigration, (Mensheviks in particular). Also important is his correspondence with European and American scholars interested in the history of socialism and the Russian Revolution. The second part of the collection consists of typescript drafts of Valentinov's writings with holograph annotations, and an untitled holograph manuscript.
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1958. (Box No. 1.)
  Membership cards of Nikolai Valentinov
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1935-1962. (Box No. 1.-5.)
  Consists primarily of correspondence on political subjects with fellow Russian socialists in the emigration, as well as with British and American scholars interested in the Russian revolutionary movement. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- WRITINGS, 1932-1960. (Box No. 6.-8)
  Typescript drafts of articles, an unfinished manuscript, and miscellaneous material used in the preparation of Valentinov's writings. Arranged by physical form and therein chronologically by title
- PRINTED MATTER, 1912-1962. (Box No. 9.)
  Clippings from Russian emigré, Soviet, and French press. Arranged alphabetically by language of publication
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1953-1960. (Photo file)
  Nine prints depicting Nikolai Valentinov and others
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1958 (Box Box No. 1)
  Membership cards for the Bibliothèque Nationale and the Association des Ecrivains Russes à Paris, 1958. Includes photographs
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1935-1962
  - General (Box 1.)
    - General
      - Undated (Folder 2)
      - 1950s (Folder 3)
      - 1960s (Folder 4)
    - Copies of Nikolai Valentinov's letters sent at his request by the International Institute of Social History, Amsterdam
      - Dan, Lydia, 1953-1962 (Folder 5)
      - Kuskova, Ekaterina, 1957 (Folder 6)
      - Stentsel', Z., 1937 (Folder 7)
  - Abramovich, Rafail
    - 1950-1953 (Folder 8)
    - 1954 (Folder 9)
    - 1955-1956 (Folder 10)
    - 1957 (Folder 11)
    - 1958 (Folder 12)
    - 1959 (Folder 13)
    - 1960 (Folder 14)
    - 1961-1963 (Folder 15)
  - Aldanov, Mark, 1954-1957 (Folder 16)
  - Aleksinskii, G., 1947-1958 (Folder 17)
  - American Committee for the Liberation of the Peoples of Russia (Vanda Pampukh), 1953-1958 (Folder 18)
  - Andreev, Nikolai, 1956-1964 (Folder 19)
  - Aronson, Gregor, 1945-1963 (Folder 20)
  - Bazili, Nikolai, 1935-1937 (Folder 21)
  - Berberova, Nina
    - 1949-1953 (Folder 22)
    - 1954-1960 (Folder 23)
  - Berlin, P., 1949-1955 (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - Blagov, Vladimir, 1954 (Folder 2)
  - Dalin, David, 1948-1962 (Folder 3)
  - Dan, Lydia.
    - 1949-1959. Includes typescript with holograph annotations by Lydia Dan, entitled "Sotsialdemokratiia v rezoliutsiiakh londonskogo s"ezda" (Folder 4)
    - 1960-1963 (Folder 5)
  - Le Figaro, 1953-1956 (Folder 6)
  - Gavri, Iurii, 1963 (Folder 7)
  - Gerua, Boris Vladimirovich, 1961 (Folder 8)
  - Goldstein, David, 1954-1962 (Folder 9)
  - Gul', Roman
    - Undated (Folder 10)
    - 1945-1950 (Folder 11)
    - 1951-1956 (Folder 12)
    - 1957-1960 (Folder 13)
    - 1961-1963 (Folder 14)
  - Haimson, Leopold
    - Undated-1959 (Folder 15)
    - 1960 (Folder 16)
    - 1961-1962 (Folder 17)
    - 1963-1964 (Folder 18)
  - Institut für Erforschung der Geschichte und Kultur der UdSSR e. V. (Box 3.)
    - 1952-1954 (Folder 1)
    - 1955 (Folder 2)
  - Jasny, N., 1960 (Folder 3)
  - Karpovich, Mikhail
    - 1948-1956 (Folder 4)
    - 1957-1959 (Folder 5)
  - KHeraskov, Ivan, 1956-1963 (Folder 6)
  - KHomiakov, G., 1959-1961 (Folder 7)
  - Kon, Vera, 1959-1962 (Folder 8)
  - Kuskova, Ekaterina
    - 1944-1949 (Folder 9)
    - 1950-1954 (Folder 10)
    - 1955 (Folder 11)
    - 1956-1958 (Folder 12)
  - Levitas, Solomon, 1953 (Folder 13)
  - Maklakov, Vasilii, 1948-1954 (Folder 14)
  - Makovskii, S., 1958 (Folder 15)
  - Mel'gunov, Sergei, 1946-1955 (Folder 16)
  - Meyer, Alfred, 1955-1957 (Folder 17)
  - Mogilevskii, V., 1956-1960 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - Monod-Herzen, Edouard, 1944-1945 (Folder 2-4)
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris
    - 1946-1949 (Folder 5)
    - 1950-1951 (Folder 6)
    - 1952 (Folder 7)
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 8)
    - 1955-1956 (Folder 9)
    - 1957-1962 (Folder 10)
  - Nivat, Georges, 1962 (Folder 11)
  - Olberg, Paul, 1954-1960 (Folder 12)
  - Pavlovskii, M., 1956-1958 (Folder 13)
  - Pipes, Richard, 1959-1962 (Folder 14)
  - Poliakov, A., n.d. (Folder 15)
  - Prokopovich, Sergei, 1939-1946 (Folder 16)
  - Raeff, Mark, 1960-1961 (Folder 17)
  - Rozenfel'd, O., 1954-1960 (Folder 18)
  - Rumanov, A.(?) and Lidiia, 1947-1960 (Folder 19)
  - Samson, Jean Paul, 1957-1960 (Folder 20)
  - Sapir, Boris, 1960 (Folder 21)
  - Sapiro, J. H., 1961-1962 (Folder 22)
  - Shapiro, Leonard, 1957-1964 (Folder 23)
  - Shub, David (Jewish Daily Forward) (Box 5.)
    - Undated and fragments (Folder 1)
    - 1944-1947 (Folder 2)
    - 1948-1950 (Folder 3)
    - 1951-1952 (Folder 4)
    - 1953-1957 (Folder 5)
  - Shvarts, S. Includes correspondence with Chekhov Publishing House, 1952-1958 (Folder 6)
  - Stentsel', E. and Z.
    - Undated and fragments (Folder 7)
    - 1944-1957 (Folder 8)
    - 1958-1960 (Folder 9)
    - 1961-1964 (Folder 10)
  - Struve, Aleksei and Gleb, 1954-1960 (Folder 11)
  - Szeftel, Marc, 1952 (Folder 12)
  - Teffi, n.d. (Folder 13)
  - Trotsky, I., 1954 (Folder 14)
  - Ul'ianov, N. (Radio Liberty), 1953-1956 (Folder 15)
  - Vel'min, Anatolii, 1953-1956 (Folder 16)
  - Vishniak, Mark
    - 1949-1957 (Folder 17)
    - 1958-1965 (Folder 18)
  - Vodov, S. (Russkaia Mysl'), 1951-1963 (Folder 19)
  - Weinbaum, Mark (Novoye Russkoe Slovo), 1951-1964 (Folder 20)
  - Wolfe, Bertram, 1958-1963 (Folder 21)
  - Wraga, R., 1962 (Folder 22)
  - Zaitsev, Boris, 1952-1963 (Folder 23)
  - Zeeler, Vladimir, 1948-1954 (Folder 24)
  - Zenzinov, Vladimir, 1947-1949 (Folder 25)
- WRITINGS, 1932-1960
  - Typescript drafts (Box 6.)
    - General. Untitled (Folder 1)
    - "Demagogiia I arifmetika", n.d. (Folder 2)
    - "Iz moei knigi Makh I Marksizm", n.d. (Folder 3)
    - "Kak raspredelialsia v 1937 g. narodnyi dokhod S.S.S.R.", n.d. (Folder 4)
    - "Men'shevizm I ego propaganda idei revoliutsionnogo samoupravleniia", n.d. (Folder 5)
    - "Men'shevizm I problema vlasti", n.d. (Folder 6)
    - "La méthode suédoise ou la méthode soviétique?", n.d. (Folder 7)
    - "Mozhno li verit' sovetskim ischisleniiam natsional'nogo dokhoda?", n.d. (Folder 8)
    - "Na grani dvukh epokh", n.d. (Folder 9-11)
    - "Natsional'nyi dokhod S.S.S.R.", n.d. (Folder 12)
    - "O frantsuzskoi revoliutsii 1936-1937: Chemu ona uchit?", n.d. (Folder 13)
    - "O 'pustom meste'", n.d. (Folder 14)
    - "Obshcherusskaia konferetsiia I Plekhanov", n.d. (Folder 15)
    - "Opasnye tsyfry I fakty", n.d. (Folder 16)
    - "Ot Aleksandra III k Leninu", n.d. (Folder 17)
    - "Pis'mo Makha", n.d. (Folder 18)
    - "Promyshlennost' v fevral'skuiu revoliutsiiu, gody voennogo kommunizma I period 1920-1923 g.g.", n.d. (Folder 19)
    - "Propaganda I istoriia", n.d. (Folder 20)
    - Review of Vasilii Zen'kovski, Istoriia russkoi filosofii, n.d. (Folder 21)
    - "Rossiia v predvoennyia gody, 1908-1913", n.d. (Folder 22)
    - "Rozhdenie men'shevizma", n.d. (Folder 23-26)
    - "Russkoe rabochee dvizhenie za 1880-1914 gody", n.d. (Box 7., Folder 1)
  - "S.S.S.R. I problema kratkosrochnogo (Folder 2)
    - "Trotskistkaia oppozitsiia I bor'ba s neiu", n.d. (Folder 3)
    - "V kadrakh velikoi tekhnicheskoi revoliutsii", n.d. (Folder 4)
    - "Vokrug Lenina", n.d. (Folder 5-7)
    - "Vtorichnye pokhorony velichaishego polkovodtsa", n.d. (Folder 8)
    - "Bor'ba za chistoe mesto", 1932 (Folder 9)
    - "Dovoennaia industriia eia uroven' I osnovnyia problemy", 1932 (Folder 10)
    - "Zagadki Liutetsii", 1932 (Folder 11)
    - "Ob umiraiushchikh zamkakh I ischezaiushchikh burzhuaznykh kvartirakh", 1933 (Folder 12)
    - "Groznyi vopros, gorodam ne khvataet vody", 1934 (Folder 13)
    - "Umiraiushchaia roskosh", 1934 (Folder 14)
    - "Zhilishchnyi vopros v Moskve I Parizhe", 1934 (Folder 15)
    - "Chudo na vostoke, piatiletnii plan I rozhdenie sovetskoi industrii", 1935 (Folder 16)
    - "Kuda idet S.S.S.R.?", 1935 (Folder 17)
    - "Vzgliad v budushchee", 1935-1936 (Folder 18-21)
    - "Ozhivshii Kreml'", 1936 (Folder 22)
    - "Russkaia derevnia I sel'skoe khoziaistvo za period 1906-1917", 1937 (Box 8., Folder 1)
    - "Biudzhet S.S.S.R.", 1937-1938 (Folder 2)
    - "Domaine des trusts et de la nationalisation", 1945 (Folder 3)
    - "Velikaia taina Kremlia", 1953 (Folder 4)
    - Memoirs, 1956. Includes, "Neobkhodimoe poiasnenie" (Folder 5-7)
    - Review of Mirovaia sotsialistichkaia sistema, 1958 (Folder 8)
    - "Otvet Denike", 1960 (Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous material entitled "Mirovaia revoliutsiia: Eia smysl, put', zakony", used in lectures, 1945-1946 (Folder 10)
  - Untitled holograph, n.d. (Folder 11-12)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1912-1962. Clippings
  - French (Box 9., Folder 1)
  - Russian
    - General - Soviet newspapers (Folder 2)
    - Novaia Zhizn' (Folder 3)
    - Novoye Russkoye Slovo (Folder 4-6)
    - Russkaia Mysl' (Folder 7)
  - Miscellany (Folder 8)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1953-1960. (Av Photo file)
  One portrait print of Nikolai Valentinov, one portrait print of IU. Dalin, one print of Lydia Dan, one portrait print of A. Potresov, four prints of Sergei Prokopovich, and one print of Elena Stensel' (envelope A)